Addison Emery Verrill Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Addison Emery Verrill Archives
1864-1926
IZAR.000940
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
10
The archives of Addison Emery Verrill, accumulated over his lifetime, notably including Yale teaching and research materials.
Verrill, Addison Emery
Biographical Sketch
Addison Emery Verrill (b. 1839, d. 1926) was born in Greenwood, Maine. Early accounts chronicle his ability as a naturalist while he was growing up in Norway, Maine, where his family moved in the early 1850s. Following his training under Louis Agassiz at Harvard University, Verrill, only 25 years old, accepted a position as Yale University's first Professor of Zoology. Thus began a career spanning more than 40 years teaching at Yale and serving as a curator at the Yale Peabody Museum. His lifelong devotion to taxonomic research resulted in the initial development of extensive collections at Yale in a wide variety of taxa.
Remarkably, Verrill published more than 350 papers and monographs in his long career, and is credited with having described more than 1,000 species of animals in virtually every major taxon. A quick review of literally every major field guide to the invertebrates of the Atlantic coast, Bermuda, the Caribbean and the tropical eastern Pacific coast will reveal a wealth of Verrill's species, which remain valid even after years of taxonomic revisions by subsequent researchers. A search of early Verrill publications documents his breadth of interests, which included parasitology, mineralogy and botany.
By any account, Verrill was considered an indefatigable worker; various biographies of him portray his incredible devotion to work, fueled by an almost inexhaustible stamina. He continued to publish large monographs well after his retirement in 1907 until his death in Santa Barbara, California, in 1926.
Description of the Material
These papers include correspondence, manuscript related material, field notes, and biographical material.
Connecticut; Maine; USA; Correspondence; Field notebooks; Manuscript materials; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1864-1926; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  These include correspondence with numerous researchers from around the world, touching on topics of evolution, systematics and zoology. Also included are correspondence from his day to day work as Curator.
  - A. Howard Clarke Correspondence. Correspondence from A.H. Clarke to A.E. Verrill., 1879-1880; 001113
    - A. Howard Clarke Correspondence. A letter from A.H. Clarke to A.E. Verrill informing him he is sending specimens (presumed to Gloucester Fisheries). He asks some questions about various lots. There are identifications in Verrill's hand on back of the letter., 13 Nov 1879; 001687
    - A. Howard Clarke Correspondence. 2 letters from A.H. Clarke to A.E. Verrill on USFC letterhead out of Gloucester, MA. One giving a list of Octocorallia from various Gloucester Fish Lots. The other discussing an odd fish., 23 Oct 1879 - 30 Sep 1880; 001114
  - Albert G. Wetherby Correspondence. Correspondence from A.G. Wetherby to A.E. Verrill., 001368
    - Albert G. Wetherby Correspondence. A letter from A.G. Wetherby containing a list of shells sent to the Museum, most appear to be freshwater. He also asks Verrill about future exchanges of West Coast shells. See Invoice Ledger., 001369
  - Alexander Emmanuel Rodolphe Agassiz Correspondence. Correspondence from A.E. Agassiz to A.E. Verrill., 1881-1886; 001093
    - Alexander Emmanuel Rodolphe Agassiz Correspondence. Letter from A.E. Agassiz to A.E. Verrill discussing Echinus, Periaster and other Blake Expedition specimens., 09 Nov 1881; 001094
    - Alexander Emmanuel Rodolphe Agassiz Correspondence. Letter from A.E. Agassiz to S.F. Baird asking the whereabouts of specimens packed and sent by A.E. Verrill. The letter must have been forwarded to A.E. Verrill., 25 Nov 1886; 001095
  - Alexander Goodman More Correspondence. Correspondence from A.G. More to A.E. Verrill., 1876; 001133
    - Alexander Goodman More Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from A.G. More to A.E. Verrill thanking Verrill for 4 paperes he sent on the "Giant Cuttle-fishes" and also discussing the identity of a Cephalopoda stranded in Kerry [Ireland?]. See Related Object in Associations tab., 26 Jul 1876; 001156
  - Alfred Merle Norman Correspondence. Correspondence from A.M. Norman to A.E. Verrill., 1870; 001135
    - Alfred Merle Norman Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from A.M. Morman to A.E. Verrill thanking him for a box of specimens he received and telling him he is readying specimens for exchange. See Related Object in Associations tab., 25 Apr 1870 - 26 Apr 1870; 001158
    - Alfred Merle Norman Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from A.M. Morman to A.E. Verrill telling him that instead of sending 2 boxes of specimens through the Smihtsonian, he is sending them direct to Yale. See Related Object in Associations tab., 30 Sep 1870; 001161
  - Alpheus Hyatt Correspondence. Correspondence from A. Hyatt to A.E. Verrill., 1893; 001226
    - Alpheus Hyatt Correspondence. A letter from A. Hyatt to A.E. Verrill informing Verrill he should not send the sponges that Verrill asked him to identify. Hyatt tells him it has been a long time since he worked on sponges and does not think himself capable of doing the work in a timely manny. He also asks Verrill if their are any sponges from Yale College still in his posession. If so, he asks that Verrill send hima list so he could return them., 21 Dec 1893; 001227
  - Alpheus Spring Packard Correspondence. Correspondence from A.S. Packard to A.E. Verrill., 1864-1926; 001136
    - Alpheus Spring Packard Correspondence. A letter from A.S. Packard to A.E. Verrill informing him he is sending the enclosed specimens. See Invoice Ledger. the letter appears to be related to the list of specimens in proximity to the letter in the Invoice Ledger., 13 Dec 1866; 001462
    - Alpheus Spring Packard Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from A.S. Packard to A.E. Verrill. Brief note about "Lutken's remarks on A. Mex." Note: D.V. Rhodes did not know who "ASP" was. See Related Object in Associations tab., 001159
  - Archibald Pride Correspondence. Correspondence from A. Pride to A.E. Verrill., 1871; 001304
    - Archibald Pride Correspondence. A letter from A. Pride inquiring if the museum would be interested in purchasing a male and female skeleton of Megaceros hibernicus (Irish Elk)., 03 Nov 1871; 001305
  - August Assmann Correspondence. Correspondence from A. Assmann to A.E. Verrill., 1867; 001418
    - August Assmann Correspondence. A letter from A. Assmann to A.E. Verrill apparently discussing Lepidoptera and Coleoptera. The letter is in German. See YPM Zoology Acc. No. 248. See Invoice Ledger., 03 Jan 1867; 001419
  - Berlin H. Wright Correspondence. Correspondence from B.H. Wright to A.E. Verrill., 1885; 001280
    - Berlin H. Wright Correspondence. A letter from B.H. Wright informing Verrill he has found crustaceans in a cistern and asking him how he can send them for identification., 27 Mar 1885; 001281
  - Byron D. Verrill Correspondence. Correspondence from B.D. Verrill to his brother, A.E. Verrill., 1871-1885; 001166
    - Byron D. Verrill Correspondence. 6 letters from B.D. Verrill to his brother, A.E. Verrill., 26 Jul 1871 - 14 Jun 1885; 001167
  - C. Ritter Correspondence. Correspondence from C. Ritter to A.E. Verrill., 1887; 001243
    - C. Ritter Correspondence. A letter from a Dr. C. Ritter to A.E. Verrill informing him he is sending a segment tape worm removed from a patient, questionably calling it Ligula, asking for a more definite identification. A Verrll note on the letter reads "supposed human parasite (not one)"., 16 Nov 1887; 001244
  - Carl F. Gissler Correspondence. Correspondence from C.F. Gissler to A.E. Verrill., 1888; 001245
    - Carl F. Gissler Correspondence. A letter from C.F. Gissler to A.E. Verrill vouching for the authenticity of the parasite sent to Verrill from Dr. C. Ritter. Apparently, Verrill had expressed doubt it was a human parasite, Gissler, however was present when it was removed from the patient. He goes on to say he thought it either a Taenia medioeannelata or a Ligula., 22 Sep 1888; 001246
  - Chalres Earle Correspondence. Correspondence from C. Earle to A.E. Verrill., 1886; 001264
    - Chalres Earle Correspondence. A letter from C. Earle informing A.E. Verrill he is sending him a coral he collected from Bermuda., 08 Dec 1886; 001265
  - Chalres Lincoln Edwards Correspondence. Correspondence from C.L. Edwards to A.E. Verrill., 1900; 001685
    - Chalres Lincoln Edwards Correspondence. A letter from C.L. Edwards informing Verrill he is sending a can of animals from the Florida Keys in thanks for Verrill giving him some Synaptas the previous December. Verrill note on envelope reads "Edwards Gorgonians sent.", 23 Apr 1900; 001686
  - Charles A. Houghton Correspondence. Correspondence from C.A. Houghton to A.E. Verrill., 1877 - 1881; 001284
    - Charles A. Houghton Correspondence. 4 letters from C.A. Houghton discussing taxidermy services rendered for numerous specimens of birds, mammals and reptiles., 10 Apr 1877 - 18 Jun 1881; 001285
    - Charles A. Houghton Correspondence. A letter from C.A. Houghton informing Verrill he is sending him the bird and mammal mounts. See Invoice Ledger., 19 Nov 1877; 001370
  - Charles Cleveland Nutting Correspondence. Correspondence from C.C. Nutting to A.E. Verrill., 1889; 001099
    - Charles Cleveland Nutting Correspondence. Letter from C.C. Nutting requesting the aid of A.E. Verrill in identifying a Gorgonacea coral from the British Virgin Islands., 22 Aug 1889; 001100
  - Charles Frederic Hartt Correspondence. Correspondence from C.F. Hartt to A.E. Verrill., 1868; 001138
    - Charles Frederic Hartt Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from C.F. Hartt to A.E. Verrill discussing Brazil and West Indian Anthozoa. See Related Object in Associations tab., 02 Mar 1868; 001162
  - Charles G. Am Ende Correspondence. Correspondence from C.G. Am Ende to A.E. Verrill., 1877; 001251
    - Charles G. Am Ende Correspondence. A letter from C.G. Am Ende to S.F. Baird, forwarded to A.E. Verrill. The letter discusses solutions of alcohol and salt created by Am Ende that can be used for the preservation of specimens., 06 Aug 1877; 001252
  - Charles Hervey Townshend Correspondence. Correspondence from C.H. Townshend to A.E. Verrill., 1893; 001272
    - Charles Hervey Townshend Correspondence. A letter from C.H. Townshend informing Verrill he is sending oysters colleced from Strattford Light in Sep 1892., 17 Jun 1893; 001273
  - Christian Frederik Lutken Correspondence. Correspondence from C.F. Lutken to A.E. Verrill., 1866-1873; 000942
    - Christian Frederik Lutken Correspondence. 15 letters from C.F. Lutken to A.E. Verrill discussing exhanges between the YPM and the Zoological Museum, Univerity of Copenhagen. They also discuss Octocorallia, Hexacorallia and Echinodermata research., 06 Feb 1866 - 24 Apr 1873; 001009
    - Christian Frederik Lutken Correspondence. A letter from C.F. Lutken discussing an exchange. He includes a list of Radiata he is sending. He also says he would send some Crustacea in the future. See Invoice Ledger., 16 Mar 1867; 001420
  - Clinton Hart Merriam Correspondence. Correspondence from C.H. Merriam to A.E. Verrill., 1883; 001517
    - Clinton Hart Merriam Correspondence. A letter from C.H. Merriam asking Verrill for help in identifying a shell he thinks is Angulus tenellus collected from Long Island, N.Y, on 24 Sep 1883., 13 Oct 1883; 001518
  - D. W. Ferguson. Correspondence from D.W. Ferguson to A.E. Verrill., 1873-1887; 001257
    - D. W. Ferguson. A letter from D.W. Ferguson to A.E. Verrill enclosing Natica heros, Astarte and Tellina. He tells Verrill he may keep them, and also says he does not have the shells in his collection that Verrill had apparently requested in a letter., 06 Dec 1873; 001258
    - D. W. Ferguson. A letter from D.W. Ferguson to A.E. Verrill discussing the an echinoderm, Meoma which Verrill was interested in. Ferguson informs him he has sold all but a few of the "light spined variety" and offers one in exchange for other echinodermata not in his collection., 09 Feb 1887; 001259
  - D.B. Delavan Correspondence. Correspondence from D.B. Delevan to A.E. Verrill., 1877; 001371
    - D.B. Delavan Correspondence. A letter from D.B. Delavan informing Verrill he may keep the Dendrophyllia nigriscens. See YPMZ Acc. No. 781. See Invoice Ledger., 19 Nov 1877; 001372
  - Daniel Addison Heald Correspondence. Correspondence from D.A. Heald to A.E. Verrill., 1881; 001278
    - Daniel Addison Heald Correspondence. A letter from D.A. Heald suggesting a Mr. John Bell to do the taxidermy of the birds for the memorial collection. He informs Verrill that if this is acceptable he will have the taxidermy done on his own expense and have the birds shipped to the College by May 1st., 05 Mar 1881; 001316
    - Daniel Addison Heald Correspondence. A letter from D.A. Heald informing Verrill the New Guinea Birds have been packed and will be sent. He also says in the future he will send specimens as he can acquire them, all in memory of his son. Also with the letter is a list of birds, presumably from New Guinea in which there is a Verrill note taht reads "Pres. G.M. Heald for Heald mem. Coll" The list has been kept with the letter., 06 Apr 1881; 001293
    - Daniel Addison Heald Correspondence. A letter from D.A. Heald informing Verrill he would like to send a collection of birds from New Zealand on condition that they be kept together in memory of his son, and be on display in time for graduation so his son's classmates could see them., 23 Feb 1881; 001314
    - Daniel Addison Heald Correspondence. A letter from D.A. Heald informing Verrill that he was mistaken in his previous letter as the birds are from New Guinea, not New Zealand., 24 Feb 1881; 001315
    - Daniel Addison Heald Correspondence. A letter from D.A. Heald thanking Verrill for his condolences on the death of his son. He informs Verrill he will donate his son's insect collection in the future., 26 Jun 1881; 001279
  - Daniel Cady Eaton Correspondence. Correspondence from D.C. Eaton to A.E. Verrill., 1871; 001195
    - Daniel Cady Eaton Correspondence. A letter from D.C. Eaton to A.E. Verrill forwarding a request for exchanges from a Maj. R.B. Beddome of India. The request for exchanges is dated 22 Dec 1869., 25 Apr 1871; 001196
  - David Starr Jordan Correspondence. Corresppondence from D.S. Jordan to A.E. Verrill., 1882 - 1883; 001289
    - David Starr Jordan Correspondence. 3 letters from D.S. Jordan to A.E. Verrill. in regards to the identification of fish., 11 Dec 1882 - 07 Feb 1883; 001290
  - Dorflinger Glass Company Correspondence. Correspondence from the Dorflinger Glass Company to A.E. Verrill., 1877; 001334
    - Dorflinger Glass Company Correspondence. A specimen jar price list sent to A.E. Verrill., 08 Mar 1877; 001335
  - E.E. Osgood Correspondence. Correspondence from E.E. Osgood to A.E. Verrill., 1903; 001312
    - E.E. Osgood Correspondence. A letter from E.E. Osgood to A.W. Phillips forwarded to Verrill by Prof. Phillips. The letter discusses the pending arrival of a collection of Himalayan Butterflies sent by Mr. Osgood., 03 Jun 1903; 001313
  - Edith J. Blakeslee Correspondence. Correspondence from E.J. Blakeslee to A.E. Verrill., 1888; 001302
    - Edith J. Blakeslee Correspondence. A letter from E.J. Blakeslee informing Verrill she is sending him a hummingbird's nest she found in a tree., 1888; 001303
  - Edward Drinker Cope Correspondence. Correspondence from E.D. Cope to A.E. Verrill., 1891; 001121
    - Edward Drinker Cope Correspondence. A letter from E.D. Cope to A.E. Verrill containing the identifications of Reptilia collected by A.H. Verrill and G.E. Verrill. In the letter Cope refers to the island as being Martinique. However they went to Dominica., 09 Mar 1891; 001123
    - Edward Drinker Cope Correspondence. A letter from E.D. Cope to A.E. Verrill containing a list of lizard species that can be found in the North Bahama Islands, as well as a herpetology reference., 20 Nov 1880; 001178
    - Edward Drinker Cope Correspondence. A letter from E.D. Cope to A.E. Verrill discussing a paper on reptiles of the West Indies for reference and informing Verrill he is finishing his work onthe North American Reptilia., 23 Feb 1891; 001122
  - Edward Norton Correspondence. Correspondence from E. Norton to A.E. Verrill., 1867; 001413
    - Edward Norton Correspondence. A letter from E. Norton informing Verrill he is sending a vairty of insects and encloses a list of named specimens for Yale College. See Invoice Ledger., 02 Dec 1867; 001414
  - Edward Palmer Correspondence. Correspondence from E. Palmer to A.E. Verrill., 001253
    - Edward Palmer Correspondence. A letter from E. Palmer to A.E. Verrill informing him he has sent a box of specimens via Prof. Marsh that contain specimens from the San Diego area. See Invoice Ledger, 10 Oct 1876; 001387
    - Edward Palmer Correspondence. A letter from E. Palmer to A.E. Verrill informing him he has sent a box of bottles for his identification. The specimens are from Panama, collected by J.M. Dow., 14 Dec; 001254
  - Edward Perceval Wright Correspondence. Correspondence from E.P. Wright to A.E. Verrill., 1870; 001132
    - Edward Perceval Wright Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from E.P. Wright to A.E. Verrill requesting a copy of Verrill's Notes on Radiata in order to help him in his preparation of the Zoological Record for 1869. He also asks for the reference for a new sponge described by Leidy. See Related Object in Associations tab., 18 May 1870; 001155
    - Edward Perceval Wright Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from E.P. Wright thanking Verrill for his letter and enclosed photograph and asks for a set of Verrill's Gorgonidae types. See Related Object in Associations tab., 23 Aug 1870; 001151
    - Edward Perceval Wright Correspondence. A transcribed copy of a letter from E.P. Wright to A.E. Verrill requesting a copy of Verrill's Part IV. Actiniaria of the North Pacific Expedition, and help tracking down a a Joseph Leidy reference. See Related Object in Associations tab., 27 Oct 1870; 001154
  - Ernest F. Coe Correspondence. Correspondence from E.F. Coe to A.E. Verrill., 1899; 001675
    - Ernest F. Coe Correspondence. A letter from E.F. Coe informing Verrill he is sending him a gallinule that he found in New Haven. Verrill note on letter says "1 fresh Florida Gallinule fresh to be mounted", 12 Jun 1899; 001676
  - Fielding Bradford Meek Correspondence. Correspondence from F.B. Meek to A.E. Verrill., 1870; 001268
    - Fielding Bradford Meek Correspondence. A letter from F.B. Meek asking Verrill for aid in identifying a fossil coral he has sent. He informs Verrill he may keep the specimen., 08 May 1870; 001269
  - Florence K. Howland Correspondence. Correspondence from F.K. Howland to A.E. Verrill., 1887; 001300
    - Florence K. Howland Correspondence. A letter from F.K. Howland to O.C. Marsh, apparently forwarded to Verrill. In it she asks if the museum would accept a collection of bird eggs left by her son. She asks that they be maintained as a unit collection, called the "Howland Collection." An accompanying letter in Verrill's hand, apparently a rough draft, says they would be willing to accept the collection provided that the museum not be required to display all the eggs as a unit in the public rooms for lack of space and out of concern for the condition of the specimens., Dec 1887; 001301
  - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. Correspondence from F.H. Bradley to A.E. Verrill. All sent from his expedition to Central America., 1866-1867; 001433
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley from Callao discussing some of the specimens he has sent. See Invoice Ledger., 01 Aug 1866; 001441
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing his collecting at the Pearl Islands. See Invoice Ledger., 01 Dec 1866; 001447
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing some of the corals he has collected. See Invoice Ledger., 01 Oct 1866; 001444
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing his collecting and telling Verrill he is leaving for Callao. See Invoice Ledger., 09 Jul 1866; 001439
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley informing Verrill he is sailing for Paita and then on to the Galapagos. See Invoice Ledger., 10 Jan 1867; 001450
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley answering a letter of Verrill's. He discusses plans for more collecting and sending specimens. See Invoice Ledger., 11 Jun 1866; 001437
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley informing Verrill he has not sent the Central American specimens yet. He also says he will be going to the Pearl Islands and possibly Callao and Valparaiso before he returns home. He also discusses the origins of some of the Sternbergh collection he has sent. See Invoice Ledger., 12 May 1866; 001436
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing the barrels of specimens he is sending. Includes localities. See Invoice Ledger., 13 Dec 1866; 001448
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley informing Verrill he is sending the wet specimens from Central America and discusses his collecting. See Invoice Ledger., 14 Jun 1866; 001438
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing his collecting in Callao and answering Verrill's letters of July and August. See Invoice Ledger., 14 Sep 1866; 001442
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley to A.E. Verrill answering a letter from Verrill and discussing his collecting. See Invoice Ledger., 21 Apr 1866; 001434
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing specimens and his collecting. See Invoice Ledger., 21 Jul 1866; 001440
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley informing Verrill he intends to go to the Galapagos Islands via Paita instead of direct from Panama. See Invoice Ledger., 22 Dec 1866; 001449
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley answering Verrill's letter of Sep 8th, and expressing his displeasure with the tone of the letter. Must read!!. See Invoice Ledger., 22 Sep 1866; 001443
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley discussing his collecting and his returning to the Pearl Islands. He requests $100 from Verrill for alcohol purchase. See Invoice Ledger., 23 Oct 1866; 001445
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley informing Verrill he is sending the Pearl Islands specimens. See Invoice Ledger., 27 Nov 1866; 001446
    - Frank Howe Bradley Correspondence. A letter from F.H. Bradley informing Verrill he will remain for another 2 months and he has sent a barrel of specimens. See Invoice Ledger., 30 Apr 1866; 001435
  - Franz Hermann Troschel Correspondence. Correspondence from F.H. Troschel to A.E. Verrill., 1869; 001012
    - Franz Hermann Troschel Correspondence. Letter from F.H. Troschel to A.E. Verrill. Letter is in german. There appears to be some request regarding Echinodermata., 26 Jan 1869; 001013
  - Fred Mather Correspondence. Correspondence from F. Mather to A.E. Verrill., 1885; 001247